So, what I'm going to do is
إذا، ما سأقوم به هو
just give you the latest episode of India's --
فقط عرض أحدث حلقة من المسلسل الهندي
maybe the world's -- longest running soap opera,
وربما أطول مسلسل قائم في العالم
which is cricket.
وهو الكريكيت
And may it run forever, because it gives people like me a living.
وأدعو أن يستمر للأبد، لأنه يوفر العمل لأمثالي
It's got everything that you'd want a normal soap opera to want:
فلديه كل ما تريده من المسلسل
It's got love, joy, happiness,
فيه الحب، المرح، والسعادة
sadness, tears, laughter,
الحزن، الدموع، الضحك
lots of deceit, intrigue.
الكثير من الخداع والتآمر
And like all good soaps, it jumps 20 years
وكجميع المسلسلات الجيدة يقفز 20 عام
when the audience interest changes.
حين يتغير إهتمام الجمهور
And that's exactly what cricket has done.
وهذا تماما ما فعله الكريكيت
It's jumped 20 years
لقد قفز 20 عام
into 20-over game.
إلى أكثر من 20 لعبة
And that's what I'm going to talk about,
وهذا ما سأتحدث عنه
how a small change
كيف أن تغييرا بسيطا
leads to a very big revolution.
يؤدي إلى تطور كبير
But it wasn't always like that.
ولكنه لم يكن دائما كذلك
Cricket wasn't always this
الكريكيت لم يكن دوما هذه
speed-driven generations game.
الرياضة السريعة للأجيال
There was a time when you played cricket,
كان هناك وقت تلعب فيه الكريكيت
you played timeless test matches,
تلعب فيه مباريات تجريبية مزمنة
when you played on till the game got over.
حين تلعب حتى تنتهي اللعبة
And there was this game in March 1939
وقد حدثة مباراة في مارس 1939
that started on the third of March
والتي بدأت في الثالث من مارس
and ended on the 14th of March.
وإنتهت في 14 مارس
And it only ended because the English cricketers
وقد إنتهت فقط لأن اللاعبين الإنجليز
had to go from Durban to Cape Town,
إضطرو للذهاب من دوربن إلى كيب تاون
which is a two-hour train journey,
وهي رحلة تستغرق ساعتين بالقطار
to catch the ship that left on the 17th,
ليلحقوا بالباخرة التي تغادر في 17 مارس
because the next ship wasn't around for a long time.
لأن الباخرة التالية كانت بعد فترة كبيرة
So, the match was ended in between.
لذا فقد انهيا المباراة في منتصفها
And one of the English batsmen said, "You know what?
وقال أحد الضاربين الإنجليز "هل تعلمون؟
Another half an hour and we would have won."
نصف ساعة أخرى وكنا سنفوز
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another half an hour after 12 days.
نصف ساعة بعد 12 يوم
There were two Sundays in between. But of course, Sundays are church days,
تخللهما يومي أحد. وبالطبع يوم الأحد يوم الكنيسة
so you don't play on Sundays. And one day it rained,
فلا نلعب يوم الأحد وقد أمطرت في أحد الأيام
so they all sat around making friends with each other.
لذا جلسوا جميعا يتسامرون
But there is a reason why India fell in love with cricket:
ولكن هناك سبب لوقوع الهند في غرام لعبة الكريكيت
because we had about the same pace of life.
ذلك أن وتيرة حياتنا كانت كذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The Mahabharata was like that as well, wasn't it?
كانت الماهابهاراتا على تلك الشاكلة، أليس كذلك؟
You fought by day, then it was sunset,
نحارب في النهار. وحين غربت الشمس
so everyone went back home.
ذهب الجميع إلى المنزل
And then you worked out your strategy,
ثم عملت على خطتكم
and you came and fought the next day, and you went back home again.
وعدت إليها من جديد اليوم التالي، وعدتم إلى المنزل مجددا
The only difference between the Mahabharata and our cricket was
الفرق الوحيد بين الماهابهاراتا والكريكيت كان
that in cricket, everybody was alive to come back and fight the next day.
أن الجميع أحياء ليأتوا في اليوم التالي ويكملوا المعركة
Princes patronize the game,
دعم الأمراء اللعبة
not because they love the game,
ليس بسبب حبهم لها
but because it was a means of ingratiating themselves
ولكن لأنها كانت طريقة لهم للإختلاط
to the British rulers.
بحكام بريطانيا
But there is one other reason why India fell in love with cricket,
ولكن هناك سبب آخر لوقوع الهند في حب الكريكيت
which was, all you needed was a plank of wood
وهو، أن كل ما تحتاج إليه هو لوح خشب
and a rubber ball, and any number of people
وكرة مطاطية، وأي عدد من الناس
could play it anywhere.
يمكنهم اللعب في أي مكان
Take a look:
إنظروا
You could play it in the dump
يمكنكم اللعب في خرابة
with some rocks over there,
مع بعض الاحجار هناك
you could play it in a little alley --
يمكنم اللعب في زقاق صغير
you couldn't hit square anywhere, because the bat hit the wall;
لا يمكنك التصويب جيدا لأي مكان، لأن المضرب يصطدم بالحائط
don't forget the air conditioning and the cable wires.
ولا تنسوا المكيفات والكابلات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You could play it on the banks of the Ganges --
يمكنكم اللعب على ضفاف الغانج
that's as clean as the Ganges has been for a long time.
هذا أنظف ما وصل إليه نهر الغانج منذ زمن بعيد
Or you could play many games in one small patch of land,
أو يمكنكم لعب العديد من المباريات في قطعة أرض صغيرة
even if you didn't know which game you were actually in.
حتى ولو لم تعرف في أيهم تلعب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As you can see, you can play anywhere.
كما ترون، يمكنكم اللعب في أي مكان
But slowly the game moved on,
ولكن تدريجيا إنتقلت اللعبة
you know, finally.
كما تعلمون، أخيرا
You don't always have five days. So, we moved on,
فأنت لا تملك دوما خمس أيام. لذا إنتقلنا
and we started playing 50-over cricket.
وبدأنا بلعب كريكيت 50 جولة
And then an enormous accident took place.
ثم وقع حادث عظيم
In Indian sport we don't make things happen,
في الرياضة الهندية نحن لا نجعل الأمور تحدث
accidents happen and we're in the right place at the right time, sometimes.
ولكن قد تحدث الأخطاء ونحن في المكان المناسب في الوقت المناسب، أحيانا
And we won this World Cup in 1983.
وقد فزنا بكأس العالم 1983
And suddenly we fell in love with the 50-over game,
وفجأة وقعنا في حب كريكيت 50 جولة
and we played it virtually every day.
ولعبنا تقريبا كل يوم
There was more 50-over cricket than anywhere.
أصبح لدينا مباريات كريكيت 50 جولة أكثر من أي مكان
But there was another big date.
ولكن كان هناك تاريخ آخر مهم
1983 was when we won the World Cup.
في 1983 حينما فزنا بكأس العالم
1991,'92, we found a finance minister
في 1991،92 وجدنا وزير مالية
and a prime minister
ورئيس وزراء
willing to let the world look at India,
يقبلوا أن ينظر العالم إلى الهند
rather than be this great country of intrigue
بدلا عن أن تكون هذا البلد الجذاب
and mystery in this closed country.
والغامض المغلق
And so we allowed multinationals into India.
لذا سمحنا للشركات الدولية الدخول إلى الهند
We cut customs duties, we reduced import duties,
خفضنا الجمارك. خفضنا رسوم الإستيراد
and we got all the multinationals coming in,
وجعلنا كل الشركات الدولية تدخل
with multinational budgets,
بميزانيات دولية
who looked at per-capita income
والتي نظرت إلى دخل الفرد
and got very excited about the possibilities in India,
وتحمست جدا للإمكانيات الهندية
and were looking for a vehicle to reach every Indian.
وبحثوا عن طريقة للوصول لكل هندي
And there are only two vehicles in India -- one real, one scripted.
وهناك طريقتين في الهند، واحدة حقيقية والثانية مشفرة
The scripted one is what you see in the movies,
المشفرة هي ما ترونه في الأفلام
the real one was cricket.
والحقيقية كانت الكريكت
And so one of my friends sitting right here in front of me,
فقام أحد أصدقائي الجالس أمامي الآن
Ravi Dhariwal from Pepsi, decided he's going to take it
رافي تريفال من بيبسي، قرر أنه سيأخذها
all over the world.
حول العالم
And Pepsi was this big revolution, because they started taking cricket all over.
وبيبسي كانت التطور الكبير. لأنهم بدأو بأخذ الكريكيت لكل مكان
And so cricket started becoming big;
وبذلك بدأ الكريكيت يكبر
cricket started bringing riches in.
بدأ الكريكيت بجذب المال
Television started covering cricket. For a long time
بدأ التلفزيون بتغطية الكريكيت. ولفترة طويلة
television said, "We won't cover cricket
قال التفزيون "لن ننقل الكريكيت
unless you pay us to cover it."
ما لم تدفعوا لنا"
Then they said, "OK,
ثم قالوا "حسنا
the next rights are sold for 55 million dollars.
الحقوق التالية ستباع بـ 55 مليون دولار.
The next rights are sold for 612 million dollars."
الحقوق التالية ستباع بـ 612 مليون دولار.
So, it's a bit of a curve, that.
لذلك هناك تطور ملموس
And then another big accident happened in our cricket.
ثم حدث مفاجأة أخرى في الكريكيت
England invented 20 overs cricket,
إخترعت إنجلترا كريكيت 30 جولة
and said, "The world must play 20 overs cricket."
وقالت العالم يجب أن يلعب كريكيت 20 جولة
Just as England invented cricket, and made the rest of the world play it.
تماما كما قامت إنجلترا بإختراع الكريكيت، وجعلت باقي العالم يلعبها
Thank God for them.
أشكر الله على وجودهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so, India had to go and play the T20 World Cup, you see.
لذا، إضطرت الهند أن تذهب وتلعب كأس العالم T20
India didn't want to play the T20 World Cup.
الهند لم ترغب بلعب كأس العالم T20
But we were forced to play it by an 8-1 margin.
ولكننا أجبرنا على اللعب بهامش 8-1
And then something very dramatic happened.
ثم حدث أمر دراماتيكي
We got to the final, and then this moment,
وصلنا إلى النهائي، ثم هذه اللحظة
that will remain enshrined forever,
والتي ستبقى مخلدة
for everybody, take a look.
للجميع، إنظروا
(Crowd cheering)
(الجماهير تهتف)
The Pakistani batsman trying to clear the fielder.
الضارب الباكستاني يحاول إخلاء المضمار
Announcer: And Zishan takes it! India wins!
المعلق: وزيشان يأخذها! الهند تفوز!
What a match for a Twenty20 final.
ما أروعها من مباراة نهائي لكأس العالم T20
India, the world champions.
الهند بطلة العالم
(Cheering)
(هتاف)
India, T20 champions.
الهند، أبطال T20
But what a game we had, M. S. Dhoni
ولكن ما أروعها من مباراة، م س دهوني
got it right in the air, but Misbah-ul-Haq, what a player.
أمسكها في الهواء، ولكن ، ما أروعه من لاعب
A massive, massive success:
نجاح باهر جدا
India, the world TT champions.
الهند، بطلة العالم TT
Harsha Bhogle: Suddenly India discovered this power of 20-overs cricket.
هارشا بهوجل: فجأة إكتشفت الهند قوة الكريكيت 20 جولة
The accident, of course, there, was that the batsman
المفاجأة هنا، طبعا، أن الضارب
thought the bowler was bowling fast.
إعتقد أن الرامي يرمي بسرعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If he had bowled fast, the ball would have gone where it was meant to go,
لو أنه رمى بسرعة لذهبت الكرة إلى موقعها المبتغى
but it didn't go. And we suddenly discovered
ولكنها لم تفعل. وفجأة إكتشفنا
that we could be good at this game.
أننا يمكن أن نبرع في هذه اللعبة
And what it also did was
وما فعله ذلك أيضا أنها
it led to a certain pride in the fact that India could be the best in the world.
جعلتنا نفخر إلى حد ما في حقيقة أن الهند يمكن أن تكون الأفضل في العالم
It was at a time when investment was coming in,
كان زمن تتدفق فيه الإستثمارات
India was feeling a little more confident about itself.
والهند تشعر بثقة أكبر في نفسها
And so there was a feeling that there was great pride
لذا تكون الشعور بأن هناك فخر كبير
in what we can do.
في ما يمككنا أن نحققه
And thankfully for all of us,
ومن حسن حظنا جميعا
the English are very good at inventing things,
الإنجليز يبرعون في إختراع الأشياء
and then the gracious people that they are,
ولا عجب من الشعب الكريم
they let the world become very good at it.
أن يسمحوا لباقي العام أن يبرع فيه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so England invented T20 cricket,
فإنجلترا إخترعت الكريكت20
and allowed India to hijack it.
وسمحوا للهند أن تختطفه
It was not like reengineering that we do in medicine,
لم يكن مثل الهندسة التي نقوم بها في الطب
we just took it straight away, as is.
فقط أخذناها مباشرة، كما هي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so, we launched our own T20 league.
وبذلك أطلقنا الدوري الهندي
Six weeks, city versus city.
ست أسابيع، مدينة ضد مدينة
It was a new thing for us. We had only ever supported our country --
وكان شيء جديد بالنسبة لنا. لقد دعمنا بلدنا
the only two areas in which India was very proud about
الموضوعين الذين تفخر جدا بهما الهند
their country, representing itself on the field.
بلدهم تمثل نفسها على الساحة
One was war, the Indian army, which we don't like to happen very often.
الأول كانت الحرب، الجيش الهندي، الذي لا نحبذ حدوثه بكثرة
The other was Indian cricket.
الآخر كان الكريكيت الهندي
Now, suddenly we had to support city leagues.
وفجأة أصبح علينا دعم دوري للمدن
But the people getting into these city leagues
ولكن الناس الذين دخلوا على هذه الدواري
were people who were taking their cues from the West.
كانوا أناس يأخذون أفكارهم من الغرب
America is a home of leagues. And they said,
أمريكا هي بيت الدواري. وقالوا
"Right, we'll build some glitzy leagues here in India."
حسنا، سنقوم ببناء دوري ساحر هنا بالهند
But was India ready for it?
ولكن هل الهند مستعدة لذلك؟
Because cricket, for a long time in India was always organized.
لأن الكريكيت، ولفترة طويلة كان دوما منظما في الهند
It was never promoted, it was never sold -- it was organized.
لم يكن أبدا مسوقا. لم يكن يباع، كان منظما
And look what they did with our beautiful, nice,
وإنظر ما الذي فعلوه بجميلتنا، اللطيفة
simple family game.
اللعبة العائلية البسيطة
All of a sudden, you had that happening.
فجأة يحدث هذا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
An opening ceremony to match every other.
حفل إفتتاح يضاهي أي حفل
This was an India that was buying Corvettes. This was an India that was buying Jaguar.
هذه كانت الهند التي تشتري الكورفيت. هذه كانت الهند التي إشترت الجاجوار
This was an India that was adding more mobile phones per month
هذه كانت الهند التي كانت تضيف جوالات شهرية
than New Zealand's population twice over.
أكثر من ضعف تعداد نيوزيلاندا
So, it was a different India.
فكانت هند مختلفة
But it was also a slightly more orthodox India
ولكنها أيضا كانت الهند التقليدية
that was very happy to be modern,
والتي سعدت بتحضرها
but didn't want to say that to people.
ولكنها لا ترغب بقول ذلك للناس
And so, they were aghast when the cheerleaders arrived.
ولذلك، كانوا مذعورين حن وصلت المشجعات
Everyone secretly watched them, but everyone claimed not to.
كان الجميع يشاهدهن سرا. ولكن الجميع كان يدعي غير ذلك
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The new owners of Indian cricket were not the old princes.
الملاك الجدد لفرق الكريكيت الهندية ليسو الأمراء القدامى
They were not bureaucrats who were forced
ليسو البروقراطيين المجبرين
into sport because they didn't actually love it;
على الرياضة لأنهم لم يحبوها في الواقع
these were people who ran serious companies.
هؤلاء كانوا أناس يديرون شركات جادة
And so they started promoting cricket big time,
لذا فقد قاموا بالتسويق للكريكيت بقوة
started promoting clubs big time.
بدأوا بالتسويق للفرق بقوة
And they've started promoting them with huge money behind it.
وبدأوا بضخ الأموال الضخمة فيها
I mean the IPL had 2.3 billion dollars
فلقد حصل الدوري الهندي على 2,3 بليون دولار
before a ball was bowled,
قبل رمي أي كرة
1.6 billion dollars for television revenue over 10 years,
دخل تلفزيوني 1,6 بليون دولار في 10 سنوات
and another 70 million dollars plus from all these franchises
وأكثر من 70 مليون من المواد التسويقية الأخرى
that were putting in money. And then they had to appeal to their cities,
والتي تجذب الأموال. ثم كان عليهم جذب مدنهم
but they had to do it like the West, right? Because we are setting up leagues.
ولكن كان عليهم فعل ذلك كالغرب أليس كذلك؟ لأننا نأسس دواري
But what they were very good at doing
ولكن ما كانوا بارعين فيه
was making it very localized.
هو جعلها محلية جدا
So, just to give you an example of how they did it --
لذا، فقط لإعطائكم مثل عن ما فعلوه
not Manchester United style promotion,
ليست دعاية مثل مانشستر يونيتد
but very Mumbai style promotion. Take a look.
ولكن دعاية بطابع مومباي، إنظروا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Of course, a lot of people said, "Maybe they dance better than they play."
بالتأكيد قال الكثير من الناس ربما يرقصون أفضل مما يلعبون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But that's all right. What it did also is it changed the way we looked at cricket.
ولكن ذلك جيد. ما فعله أيضا هو أنها غيرت الطريقة التي ننظر بها إلى الكريكيت
All along, if you wanted a young cricketer,
في الماضي، لو أردت لاعب شاب
you picked him up from the bylanes of your own little locality,
تختاره من محيطك الصغير المحلي
your own city, and you were very proud
من مدينتك، وكنت فخورا جدا
of the system that produced those cricketers.
من النظام الذي أنتج هؤلاء اللاعبين
Now, all of the sudden, if you were to bowl a shot --
الآن، فجأة، لو أردت أن ترمي رمية
if Mumbai were to bowl a shot, for example,
لو أن مومباي ترغب في رمي رمية مثلا
they needn't go to Kalbadevi
لا يحتاجون إلى الذهاب إلى كالبديفي
or Shivaji Park or somewhere to source them,
أو شيفاجي أو مكان ما لتحضيرهم
they could go to Trinidad.
يمكنهم الذهاب إلى ترينيداد
This was the new India, wasn't it? This was the new world,
هذه هي الهند الحديثة أليس كذلك؟ هذا هو العالم الجديد
where you can source from anywhere
حيث يمكنك التوريد من أي مكان
as long as you get the best product at the best price.
حيث تحصل على أفضل المنتجات بأفضل الأسعار
And all of a sudden, Indian sport had awakened to the reality
وفجأة إستيقظت الرياضة الهندية للواقع
that you can source the best product for the best price
بأنك تستطيع توفير أفضل منتج بأفضل سعر
anywhere in the world.
من أي مكان في العالم
So, the Mumbai Indians flew in Dwayne Bravo from Trinidad and Tobago,
فأحضر الهنود الممباييون دوايني برافو من ترينداد إلى توباجو
overnight. And when he had to go back to represent
في ليلة. وحين إضطر للعودة ليمثل
the West Indies, they asked him, "When do you have to reach?"
إلى جزر الهند الغربية، سألوه "متى تحتاج أن تصل إلى هناك؟
He said, "I have to be there by a certain time, so I have to leave today."
فقال "أحتاج أن أصل هناك في وقت معين، لذا أحتاج أن أغادر اليوم
We said, "No, no, no. It's not about when you have to leave;
فقلنا " لا لا لا. الأمر لا يتعلق بمتى تحتاج أن تغادر
it's about when do you have to reach there?"
لإنه يتعلق بمتى تحتاج أن تصل
And so he said, "I've got to reach on date X."
فقال " أحتاج أن أصل في يوم أكس
And they said, "Fine, you play to date X, minus one."
فقالوا "حسنا، فلتلعب في يوم أكس ناقص واحد
So, he played in Hyderabad, went, straight after the game,
فلعب في حيدرأباد، غادر بعد المباراة مباشرة
went from the stadium to Hyderabad airport,
غادر من الاستاد إلى مطار حيدرأباد
sat in a private corporate jet -- first refueling in Portugal,
صعد في طائرة خاصة، توقفت في البرتغال
second refueling in Brazil; he was in West Indies in time.
ثم في البرازيل. ووصل إلى جزر الهند الغربية في وقته
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Never would India have thought on this scale before.
لم تكن الهند لتفكر بهذا الحجم في السابق
Never would India have said, "I want a player to play
لم تكن الهند لتقول "أحتاج لاعبا ليلعب
one game for me, and I will use a corporate jet
مباراة لي، ثم سأستخدم طائرة خاصة
to send him all the way back to Kingston, Jamaica
لأرسله إلى كينجستون جامايكا
to play a game."
ليلعب مباراة
And I just thought to myself,
وفكرت
"Wow, we've arrived somewhere in the world, you know?
واو، لقد وصلنا إلى مكان ما في العالم
We have arrived somewhere. We are thinking big."
لقد وصلنا إلى مكان ما. نحن نفكر بضخامة
But what this also did was it started
ولكن ما فعله ذلك أنه بدأ
marrying the two most important things in Indian cricket,
في تزويج أهم أمرين في كريكيت الهند
which is cricket and the movies in Indian entertainment.
وهما الكريكيت، وترفيه الأفلام الهندية
There is cricket and the movies.
هناك كريكيت والأفلام
And they came together because people in the movies
وقد إجتمعا لأن صناع الأفلام
now started owning clubs.
بدأو بإمتلاك الأندية
And so, people started going to the cricket to watch Preity Zinta.
وبذلك، بدأ الناس يذهبون إلى الكريكيت ليشاهدوا بريتي زينتا
They started going to the cricket to watch Shah Rukh Khan.
بدأوا بالذهاب إلى الكريكيت ليشاهدوا شاهوخ خان
And something very interesting happened.
وحدث أمر مثير جدا
We started getting song and dance in Indian cricket.
حصلنا على الغناء والرقص في الكريكيت الهندية
And so it started resembling the Indian movies more and more.
وأصبحت تشبه الأفلام الهندية أكثر فأكثر
And of course, if you were on Preity Zinta's team --
وبالطبع، لو أنك في فريق بريتي زينتا
as you will see on the clip that follows -- if you did well,
كما سترون في المقطع التالي، لو أنك لعبت جيدا
you got a hug from Preity Zinta.
حصلت على معانقة من بريتي زناتا
So that was the ultimate reason to do well. Take a look --
فكان هذا السبب الأهم للأداء المتميز. إنظروا
everyone's watching Preity Zinta.
الجميع يشاهد بريتي زناتا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And then of course there was Shah Rukh playing the Kolkata crowd.
وبالطبعا كان هناك شاهروخ يلعب بجماهير كولكتا
We'd all seen matches in Kolkata,
جميعنا شاهد مباريات في كولكتا
but we'd never seen anything like this:
ولكننا لم نر أبدا شيء كهذا
Shah Rukh, with the Bengali song, getting the audiences all worked up
شاهروخ يحمس الجماهير بالإغنية البنغالية
for Kolkata -- not for India, but for Kolkata.
ليس للهند ولكن لكولكتا
But take a look at this.
ولكن إنظروا إلى هذا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
An Indian film star hugging a Pakistani cricketer
ممثل أفلام هندي يحتضن لاعب كريكيت باكستاني
because they'd won in Kolkata.
لأنهم فازو في كولكتا
Can you imagine?
هل تتصورون؟
And do you know what the Pakistani cricketer said?
وهل تعلمون ما قاله اللاعب الباكستاني؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
"I wish I was playing for Preity Zinta's team."
تمنيت لو أنني ألعب في فريق بريتي زنتا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I thought I'd take this opportunity --
ولكنني فكرت بأن أستغل هذه الفرصة
there's a few people from Pakistan in here.
هناك البعض من باكستان هنا
I'm so happy that you're here
أنا سعيد جدا لوجودكم
because I think we can show that we can both be together and be friends, right?
لأنني أعتقد أننا نستطيع إظهار أننا يمكن أن نكون سوية وأن نكون أصدقاء
We can play cricket together, we can be friends.
يمكننا لعب الكريكيت معا، يمكننا أن نصبح أصدقاء
So thank you very much for coming, all of you from Pakistan.
فشكرا جزيلا لحضوركم من باكستان
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There was criticism too because they said,
كان هناك إنتقادات أيضا لأنهم قالوا
"Players are being bought and sold?
اللاعبين يباعوا ويشتروا؟
Are they grain?
هل هم حبوب؟
Are they cattle?"
هل هم قطيع؟
Because we had this auction, you see.
لأننا أقمنا مزادا
How do you fix a price for a player?
كيف تحدد قيمة لاعب؟
And so the auction that followed
وفي المزاد التالي
literally had people saying,
كان هناك من يقولون
"Bang! so many million dollars for so-and-so player."
هاكم! ملايين الدولات من أجل اللاعب فلان وفلان
There it is.
ها هي
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Auctioneer: Going at 1,500,000 dollars. Chennai.
العارض: الآن 1,500,000 دولار
Shane Warne sold for 450,000 dollars.
تم البيع 450,000 دولار
HB: Suddenly, a game which earned its players 50 rupees a day --
فجأة، لعبة كانت توفر لاعبها 50 روبية في اليوم
so 250 rupees for a test match,
أو 250 روبية لمباراة تجريبية
but if you finish in four days you only got 200.
ولكنك لو إنتهيت في أربعة أيام حصلت على 200 فقط
The best Indian players who played every test match --
أفضل اللاعبين الهنود الذين لعبوا جميع المباريات
every one of the internationals, the top of the line players --
كل واحد من الدوليين، أفضل اللاعبين
standard contracts are 220,000 dollars in a whole year.
العقود الأولية تبدأ من 220,000 دولار في العام
Now they were getting 500,000 for six days' work.
الآن يحصلون على 500,000 في ست أيام عمل فقط
Then Andrew Flintoff came by from England,
قم أتى أندرو فلينتوف من إنجلترا
he got one and a half million dollars, and he went back and said,
حصل على مليون ونصف دولار وعاد قائلا
"For four weeks, I'm earning more than Frank Lampard and Steven Gerrard,
في أربعة أسابيع، حصلت على أكثر من فرانك لامبارد وستيفن جيرارد
and I'm earning more than the footballers, wow."
وأنا أحصل على أكثر من لاعبي كرة القدم
And where was he earning it from? From a little club in India.
ومن أين كان يحصل على ذلك؟ من فريق صغير في الهند
Could you have imagined that day would come?
هل كنتم لتوقعوا ذلك اليوم؟
One and a half million dollars for six weeks' work.
مليون ونصف دولار في ست أسابيع عمل
That's not bad, is it?
ليس سيئا
So, at 2.3 billion dollars before the first ball was bowled.
فبدأ من 2,3 بليون دولار قبل أول رمية
What India was doing, though, was benchmarking
ما كانت تقوم به الهند هو تقييم
itself against the best in the world,
نفسها مقابل الأفضل في العالم
and it became a huge brand.
وأصبحت ماركة عملاقة
Lalit Modi was on the cover of Business Today.
لاليت مودي ظهر على غلاف مجلة بزنيس تودي
IPL became the biggest brand in India
أصبح الدوري الهندي أكبر ماركة في الهند
and, because our elections, had to be moved to South Africa,
وبسبب إنتخاباتنا إضطرت إلى الإنتقال إلى جنوب أفريقيا
and we had to start the tournament in three weeks.
ونحتاج إلى بدأ الدوري خلال ثلاث أسابيع
Move a whole tournament to South Africa in three weeks.
ننقل بطولة كاملة إلى جنوب أفريقيا في ثلاث أسابيع
But we did it. You know why?
ولكننا قمنا بذلك. هل تعلمون السبب؟
Because no country works as slowly as we do
لأنه لا توجد دولة تعمل ببطئنا
till three weeks before an event,
إلى ثلاث أسابيع قبل الحدث
and nobody works fast as we do in the last three weeks.
ولا يعمل أحد بسرعتنا في الأسابيع الثلاث الأخيرة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Our population, which for a long time we thought was a problem,
تعدادنا، والذي ظننا لمدة طويلة نعتقد بأنه مشكلة
suddenly became our biggest asset
فجأة أصبح أكبر ما يميزنا
because there were more people watching --
لأن عدد المشاهدين في تزايد
the huge consuming class --
الطبقة المستهلكة الضخمة
everybody came to watch the cricket.
الجميع جاء ليشاهد الكريكيت
We'd also made cricket the only sport in India,
وجعلنا الكريكيت أيضا الرياضة الوحيدة في الهند
which is a pity, but in India every other sport
وهو أمر مؤسف ، ولكن في الهند كل رياضة أخرى
pushes cricket to become big,
تدفع الكريكيت لتنمو
which is a bit of a tragedy of our times.
وهي نوعا ما من مآسي زمننا
Now, this last minute before I go --
الآن، في هذه الدقيقة الأخيرة قبل أن أذهب
there's a couple of side effects of all this.
هناك بعض النتائج الجانبية لكل هذا
For a long time, India was this country of poverty,
لزمن طويل، كانت الهند دولة للفقر
dust, beggars,
الغبار، المتسولين
snake charmers, filth,
سحرة الثعابين ، القذارة
Delhi belly -- people heard Delhi belly stories before they came.
دلهعي بيلي -- فقد سمع الناس عن قصص فلم دلهي بيلي قبل أن يأتو
And, all of a sudden, India was this land of opportunity.
وفجأة، أصبحت أرض الفرص
Cricketers all over the world said,
الكريكيت حول العالم قال
"You know, we love India. We love to play in India."
نحن نحب الهند. ونحب أن نلعب في الهند
And that felt good, you know?
وذلك شعور جميل
We said, "The dollar's quite powerful actually."
قلنا "الدولار قوي نوعا ما
Can you imagine, you've got the dollar on view
هل تتخيلون أن يوضع الدولار في الميزان
and there's no Delhi belly in there anymore.
ولا يوجد ديلهي بيلي
There's no filth, there's no beggars, all the snake charmers have vanished,
لا توجد قذارة، لا يوجد متسولون. جميع سحرة الثعابين إختفوا
everybody's gone. This tells you how the capitalist world rules.
ذهب الجميع. هذا يريكم كيف يحكم العالم الرأسمالي
Right so, finally,
وفي النهاية
an English game that India usurped a little bit,
لعبة إنجليزية تغتصبها نوعا ما الهند
but T20 is going to be the next missionary in the world.
ولكن T20 ستكون المبشر الجديد في العالم
If you want to take the game around the world,
إذا أردت أخذ اللعبة حول العالم
it's got to be the shortest form of the game.
يجب أن تكون أقصر نسخة من اللعبة
You can't take a timeless test to China and sit through 14 days with no result in the end,
لا يمكنك أخذ الإختبار غير المنتهي إلى الصين وتجلس 14 يوم دون نتائج
or you can't take it all over the world.
كما لا يمكنك أخذها حول العالم
So that's what T20 is doing.
هذا ما تفعله T20
Hopefully, it'll make everyone richer, hopefully it'll make the game bigger
نأمل أن تجعل الجميع أغنى، ونأمل أن تجعل اللعبة أكبر
and hopefully it'll give cricket commentators more time in the business.
ونأمل أنها ستعطي معلقي الكريكيت فترة أطول في الصناعة
Thank you very much. Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا. شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)